There we have learned about the selection sort algorithm.
Now let's implement it and see.
We start by include a studio that age and we create a new method called swab the swab method that we
have learned about it in many videos.
Its role is to swab the value of the first argument to that or the first parameter with the value of
the second parameter and the second parameter with the first.
So we start swapping the X with Y and Y with X Y creating a temporary item, temporary integer call
and taking it cold, damp and taking into consideration the value of X.
And X now becomes Y.
And assigning Y to that temp.
So this is the algorithm behind swapping.
OK.
Now we create a new method, this method.
It's returning type is void and cold selection sort into took into the perimeter into an array.
Variable that we had with the rate that we are going to sort and and the size of this array, we can
like remove the and and the second parameter because we can get that this and or the size by the best
parameter, but best array, which is a rate of length.
But it's the same.
So if you prefer just a passing rate that you want to select, sort about an algorithm and apply it
on it.
So just consider passing one argument and one parameter.
And I and J and minimum I the X, we will see these variables in action by creating one by one move
boundary of unsorted array.
We need an outer loop that starts from zero to end minus one.
And this is logic because we need to pass through all the elements of the unsorted array, and we start
by selecting and finding the minimum element in unsorted array.
In order to do that, we need to assign the minimum ID X to AI, and we start making a nested loop that
goes through from J Equal I +1.
So we see guys.
We considered the first element is fully sorted or there, if obviously we are on the second iteration
we consider I +1, which is I is equal to the second iteration, which is one cell, one plus one.
We consider the first two elements are fully fully sorted.
So here is the trick behind this election sort.
This is the trick.
We start from Jay Equal to I +1 and Jay less than an OK.
This is a very important trick.
If less than a rate at minimum, at minimum I the X, that rate in this indexed minimum might the X,
we are going to change it.
What we are going to make the minimum now at Index X equal to.
Now we swab or swept the found minimum element with the first element, how to swab the two elements
we call the swab and we pass that to arguments.
We need to swab this element at the array and the minimum i.e. the X and the swab being the element
at array at index high.
So we see guys how we need to and how we done that, swapping by calling them swab.
Function, OK.
Now we have done with the selection sort, this is very important to understand that we go through all
the elements using this outer loop and this inner loop starts from J Eye plus one eye plus one.
OK.
This is very important and we start swapping if the minimum is if the array at index is less than that
at minimum at index minimum idea.
OK.
This is the algorithm.
Now, let's bring the area, we have seen this in the previous video, which took in the perimeter array
and the size of it.
And we start printing it, using it for driver program to test the functions.
We need to create an entry that we are going to short here and the inside and an is equal to the size
of that right over to the size of their day and year that it will calculate the size of that right now.
We passed the selection sought selection.
Sort this.
Well, make is will apply the selection sort algorithm on this array and start printing this sorted
out.
OK.
This is the implementation of the selection sort in sea, and let's move in the next video to solve
the exercise about this election.
Sort and implement it in Java I.D. and.